For a long time in my life,
لفترة طويلة من حياتي
I felt like I'd been living two different lives.
أحسست كأنني كنت أعيش حياتين مختلفتين
There's the life that everyone sees,
هناك حياة يراها الجميع
and then there's the life that only I see.
وهناك حياة لا يراها إلا أنا فقط.
And in the life that everyone sees,
فالحياة التي يراها الجميع
who I am is a friend,
هي أنا كصديق
a son, a brother,
و كأخ وكابن
a stand-up comedian and a teenager.
و ككوميدي و كمراهق.
That's the life everyone sees.
هذا ما يراه الجميع.
If you were to ask my friends and family to describe me,
إدا طلبتم من أصدقائي و عائلتي أن يصفوني،
that's what they would tell you.
فذلك ما سيقولونه لكم.
And that's a huge part of me. That is who I am.
وهذا جزء كبير من حياتي. هدا ما أنا عليه.
And if you were to ask me to describe myself,
وإذا طلبتم منّي أن أصف لكم نفسي،
I'd probably say some of those same things.
فمن الممكن أن أجيبكم بنفس القول.
And I wouldn't be lying,
ولن أكون كاذبا في ذلك،
but I wouldn't totally be telling you the truth, either,
لكن قولي سيكون مجانبا كليا للحقيقة،
because the truth is,
لأنّ الحقيقة هي
that's just the life everyone else sees.
أنّ هذه هي الحياة التي يراها الجميع.
In the life that only I see, who I am,
في الحياة التي أراها أنا فقط
who I really am,
وما أنا حقا عليه
is someone who struggles intensely with depression.
هي أنني شخص يكافح بإستمرار ضد الإكتئاب.
I have for the last six years of my life,
وهو أمر حصل لي في السنوات الست الأخيرة،
and I continue to every day.
وأستمر في ذلك يوميا.
Now, for someone who has never experienced depression
بالنسبة لشخص لم يختبر شعور الإكتئاب من قبل
or doesn't really know what that means,
ولم يعرف حقا ما هو،
that might surprise them to hear,
ربما سيفاجئه سماع هذا
because there's this pretty popular misconception
لأن الفهم المغلوط السائد
that depression is just being sad
هو أن الإكتئاب هو فقط أن تكون حزينا
when something in your life goes wrong,
عندما يحصل لك شيء سيء في حياتك،
when you break up with your girlfriend,
عند إنفصالك عن حبيبتك مثلا،
when you lose a loved one,
أو تفقد أحد أحبتّك،
when you don't get the job you wanted.
أوعندما لا تحصل على الوظيفة التي تحلم بها.
But that's sadness. That's a natural thing.
لكن هذا حزن. وهو أمر طبيعي
That's a natural human emotion.
هذا شعور إنساني طبيعي
Real depression isn't being sad
الإكتئاب فعليّ ليس أن تكون حزينا
when something in your life goes wrong.
عند حدوث شي سيء في حياتك.
Real depression is being sad
الإكتئاب هو أن تكون حزينا
when everything in your life is going right.
عندما يسير كل شيء في حياتك بشكل جيد.
That's real depression, and that's what I suffer from.
هذا هو الإكتئاب حقا، وهذا ما أعاني منه.
And to be totally honest,
ولأكون كليا صريحا معكم،
that's hard for me to stand up here and say.
أنه من الصعب علي أن أقف هنا و أقول
It's hard for me to talk about,
إنه من الصعب علي أن أتحدت عن ذلك،
and it seems to be hard for everyone to talk about,
ويبدو أنه يصعب على أي كان أن يتكلم عن ذلك،
so much so that no one's talking about it.
لدرجة أن لا أحد يتحدث عن ذلك.
And no one's talking about depression, but we need to be,
ولا أحد يتحدت عن الإكتئاب، لكننا نحتاج للقيام بذلك،
because right now it's a massive problem.
لأنّه الآن مشكلة عويصة .
It's a massive problem.
إنه مشكلة عويصة .
But we don't see it on social media, right?
لكننا لا نرى ذلك في وسائل التواصل الإجتماعي ,
We don't see it on Facebook. We don't see it on Twitter.
لا نرى ذلك على الفايسبوك، ولا على التويتر.
We don't see it on the news, because it's not happy,
لا نرى ذلك في الأخبار، لأنه ليس أمرا سعيداً،
it's not fun, it's not light.
ولا مسليا. ولا خفيفاً.
And so because we don't see it, we don't see the severity of it.
ولأننا لا نرى ذلك، لا نرى خطورة ذلك.
But the severity of it and the seriousness of it is this:
ولكن خطورة و جدية هذا الأمر:
every 30 seconds,
أنه في كل 30 ثانية
every 30 seconds, somewhere,
كل 30 ثانية، في مكان ما،
someone in the world takes their own life
يفقد شخص في هذا العالم حياته
because of depression,
بسبب الإكتئاب.
and it might be two blocks away, it might be two countries away,
قد يكون ذلك على بعد مبنيين، أو بلدين منك،
it might be two continents away, but it's happening,
قد يكون ذلك على بعد قارّتين منك، لكنه يحدث،
and it's happening every single day.
ويحدث بصفة يومية.
And we have a tendency, as a society,
ولدينا نزعة في مجتمعنا
to look at that and go, "So what?"
حيت أننا نرى ذلك ونقول:"ماذا في ذلك"
So what? We look at that, and we go, "That's your problem.
ماذا في ذلك؟ نرى ذلك ونعلق" هذه مشكلتك.
That's their problem."
تلك مشكلتهم ."
We say we're sad and we say we're sorry,
نقول أننا حزينون وأننا متأسفون،
but we also say, "So what?"
لكننا نقول أيضا "ماذا في ذلك؟"
Well, two years ago it was my problem,
قبل سنتين كانت هذه مشكلتي،
because I sat on the edge of my bed
لأنني جلست على حافة سريري
where I'd sat a million times before
المكان الدي جلست فيه ملايين المرات من قبل
and I was suicidal.
وكنت أرغب في الإنتحار.
I was suicidal, and if you were to look at my life on the surface,
كنت أود الإنتحار، وإذا نظرتم لشريط حياتي،
you wouldn't see a kid who was suicidal.
لن يخطر على بالك أنّ طفلا يفكّر في الانتحار.
You'd see a kid who was the captain of his basketball team,
سترون طفلا كان قائد فريقه في كرة السلة،
the drama and theater student of the year,
طالب السنة في المسرح والدراما،
the English student of the year,
طالب السنة في الإنجليزية،
someone who was consistently on the honor roll
شخص كان اسمه دائما في قائمة الشرف
and consistently at every party.
و حاضرا في كلّ حفلة.
So you would say I wasn't depressed, you would say
إذن ستقولون أنني لم أكن مكتئبا، ستقولون
I wasn't suicidal, but you would be wrong.
أنني لم أكن على وشك الإنتحار، لكنكم مخطؤون
You would be wrong. So I sat there that night
ستكونون مخطئين. ذات ليلة جلست
beside a bottle of pills with a pen and paper in my hand
بجوار قارورة حبوب مع ورقة وقلم في يدي
and I thought about taking my own life
وفكرت في إنهاء حياتي
and I came this close to doing it.
وكنت على مقربة من فعل ذلك.
I came this close to doing it.
كنت على مفربة من فعل ذلك
And I didn't, so that makes me one of the lucky ones,
ولم أفعل ذلك، وهذا يجعلني واحدا من أكثر المحظوظين
one of the people who gets to step out on the ledge
واحد من الأشخاص الذين خطوا إلى الحافة
and look down but not jump,
ونظروا إلى الأسفل لكن لم يقفزوا
one of the lucky ones who survives.
واحد من المحظوظين الذين يزالون على قيد الحياة.
Well, I survived, and that just leaves me with my story,
أنا على قيد الحياة، و معي قصّتي الخاصة بي،
and my story is this:
و هي كالآتي:
In four simple words, I suffer from depression.
باختصار شديد، فأنا أعاني من الإكتئاب.
I suffer from depression,
اعاني من الإكتئاب
and for a long time, I think,
وذلك لمدة طويلة، وعلى ما أعتقد
I was living two totally different lives,
لقد عشت حياتين مختلفتين تماما
where one person was always afraid of the other.
حيث كل شخص فيها خائف من الآخر.
I was afraid that people would see me for who I really was,
كنت خائفا أن يراني الناس على الحقيقة التي أنا عليها،
that I wasn't the perfect, popular kid in high school everyone thought I was,
وأنني لم أكن الشاب الأفضل ولا الأكتر شعبية في التانوية كما يعتقد الكل،
that beneath my smile, there was struggle,
لأنه وراء إبتسامتي، كان هناك صراع
and beneath my light, there was dark,
ووراء الضوء، كان هناك صراع،
and beneath my big personality just hid even bigger pain.
و وراء شخصيتي العظيمة يختبؤ ألم كبير.
See, some people might fear girls not liking them back.
بعض الناس يخشون أن يفقدوا إعجاب الفتيات بهم.
Some people might fear sharks. Some people might fear death.
بعض الناس يخشون أسماك القرش. البعض يخشون الموت.
But for me, for a large part of my life, I feared myself.
ولكن بالنسبة لي، في جزء كبير من حياتي، كنت أخشى نفسي.
I feared my truth, I feared my honesty, I feared my vulnerability,
أخشى حقيقتي، أخشى صراحتي، أخشى ضعفي.
and that fear made me feel
وهدا الخوف جعلني أحس
like I was forced into a corner,
كأنني وضعت نفسي في عزلة،
like I was forced into a corner and there was only one way out,
كأنني وضعت نفسي زاوية وكانت هناك فقط طريقة واحدة للخروج منها،
and so I thought about that way every single day.
وفكرت في ذلك بتلك الطريقة كل يوم.
I thought about it every single day,
فكرت في الأمر يوميّا،
and if I'm being totally honest, standing here
ولأكون صادقا معكم وأنا واقف هنا
I've thought about it again since, because that's the sickness,
فكرت في ذلك مرة أخرى، لأنّ هذا هو المرض،
that's the struggle, that's depression,
هذه هي المعاناة، هذا هو الإكتئاب،
and depression isn't chicken pox.
والاكتئاب ليس مرض جدري الماء.
You don't beat it once and it's gone forever.
لن تهزمه في مرة واحد ولن يذهب للأبد.
It's something you live with. It's something you live in.
إنه أمر تعيش وتتعايش معه.
It's the roommate you can't kick out. It's the voice you can't ignore.
إنّه الحجرة التي لا يمكنك رميها بعيدا . إنه صوت لا يمكنك تجاهله.
It's the feelings you can't seem to escape,
إنّه شعور لا تستطيع أن تهرب منه،
the scariest part is that after a while,
الجزء الأكثر رعبا هو أنّه بعد فترة من الوقت،
you become numb to it. It becomes normal for you,
تصبح مخدرا بذلك. يصبح من الطبيعي بالنسبة لك،
and what you really fear the most
و يصبح أكثر ما تخشاه
isn't the suffering inside of you.
ليس ما تعانيه أنت داخليا
It's the stigma inside of others,
بل النظرات داخل الآخرين،
it's the shame, it's the embarrassment,
انه الخزي، انه الحرج،
it's the disapproving look on a friend's face,
انها نظرة الاعتراض على وجه صديق،
it's the whispers in the hallway that you're weak,
انها همسات في الأروقة أنك ضعيف،
it's the comments that you're crazy.
انها التعليقات أنك مجنون.
That's what keeps you from getting help.
هذا ما يبقيك تطلب الحصول على المساعدة.
That's what makes you hold it in and hide it.
هذا ما يجعلك تتحفظ على ذلك وتخفيه.
It's the stigma. So you hold it in and you hide it,
انها وصمة عار. لذلك تتحفظ وتخفي ذلك،
and you hold it in and you hide it,
وبالتالي تتحفظ على الأمر و تخفيه،
and even though it's keeping you in bed every day
وعلى الرغم من أنه يبقيك في السرير كل يوم
and it's making your life feel empty no matter how much you try and fill it,
وانه يجعلك تشعرأن حياتك فارغة مهما حاولت ملأها،
you hide it, because the stigma in our society
تخفي ذلك، لأنّ نظرة مجتمعنا
around depression is very real.
حول الاكتئاب حقيقية جدا.
It's very real, and if you think that it isn't, ask yourself this:
أنها حقيقية جداً، وإذا كنت تعتقد أنها ليست كذلك، اسأل نفسك التّالي:
Would you rather make your next Facebook status
هل يمكنك في الواقع على حسابك في الفايسبوك
say you're having a tough time getting out of bed
أن تقول أنك كنت تواجه صعوبة في مغادرة االسرير
because you hurt your back
لأنك آلمت ظهرك
or you're having a tough time getting out of bed every morning
أو أنّك تواجه صعوبة في مغادرة السرير كل صباح
because you're depressed?
لأنك مكتئب؟
That's the stigma, because unfortunately,
تلك هي وصمة العار، لأنّنا لسوء الحظ،
we live in a world where if you break your arm,
نعيش في عالم حيث إذا قمت بقطع ذراعك،
everyone runs over to sign your cast,
فإنّ الجميع يركض لرؤية حالتك،
but if you tell people you're depressed, everyone runs the other way.
ولكن إذا قلت للناس أنّك مكتئب، يركض الجميع في الإتجاه المعاكس.
That's the stigma.
هذه هي وصمة العار.
We are so, so, so accepting of any body part breaking down
نحن نتقبّل فكرة أن يتعطّل أيّ عضو من الجسد
other than our brains. And that's ignorance.
بخلاف ادمغتنا. وهذا هو الجهل.
That's pure ignorance, and that ignorance has created
وهذا هو لب الجهل، وقد أوجد هذا الجهل
a world that doesn't understand depression,
عالما لا يفهم الاكتئاب،
that doesn't understand mental health.
لا يفهم عن الصحة العقلية.
And that's ironic to me, because depression
وأنّه من دواعي السخرية بالنسبة لي، أن الاكتئاب
is one of the best documented problems we have in the world,
هو واحد من أفضل المشاكل الموثقة لدينا في العالم،
yet it's one of the least discussed.
مع ذلك فهو الأقل مناقشة.
We just push it aside and put it in a corner
ونحن فقط نرميه جانبا ونضعه في زاوية
and pretend it's not there and hope it'll fix itself.
ونتظاهر بأنه غير موجود، ونأمل أنه سوف يصلح نفسه بنفسه .
Well, it won't. It hasn't, and it's not going to,
حسنا، ذلك لم ولن يحدث،
because that's wishful thinking,
لأنّ ذلك التّفكير غير واقعيّ،
and wishful thinking isn't a game plan, it's procrastination,
والتمني ليس خطة، إنّه مماطلة،
and we can't procrastinate on something this important.
ونحن لا يمكننا المماطلة في أمر بهذه الأهميّة.
The first step in solving any problem
الخطوة الأولى لحلّ أي مشكلة
is recognizing there is one.
هي إدراكه أولا .
Well, we haven't done that, so we can't really expect
و بما أنّنا لم يسبق لنا أن قمنا بذلك فلا يمكننا توقّع
to find an answer when we're still afraid of the question.
العثور على إجابة في حين أنّنا لا نزال خائفين من السؤال.
And I don't know what the solution is.
انا لا أعرف ما الحل.
I wish I did, but I don't -- but I think,
وأود لو كنت أعرف، لكنني أعتقد
I think it has to start here.
و أفكّر أنّه لا بدّ من البدأ من هنا.
It has to start with me, it has to start with you,
لا بدّ أن يبدأ معي، يجب أن يبدأ الحل معك،
it has to start with the people who are suffering,
يجب أن يبدأ مع النّاس الذي يعانون،
the ones who are hidden in the shadows.
الذين يتخفّون في الظلام.
We need to speak up and shatter the silence.
نحن بحاجة إلى التحدث وتحطيم جدار الصمت.
We need to be the ones who are brave for what we believe in,
نحتاج أن نكون نحن الجريئين بما نؤمن به،
because if there's one thing that I've come to realize,
لأنّني لو أدركت شيئا فهو أنّ
if there's one thing that I see as the biggest problem,
ما أرى كونه المشكل الأكبر
it's not in building a world
هو ليس بناء عالم
where we eliminate the ignorance of others.
حيث نقضي على جهل الآخرين.
It's in building a world where we teach the acceptance of ourselves,
بل في بناء عالم نتعلّم فيه تقبّل أنفسنا،
where we're okay with who we are,
حيث نكون متفاهمين مع ذواتنا،
because when we get honest,
لأنّنا عندما نصبح صادقين،
we see that we all struggle and we all suffer.
سوف نرى أنّ علينا جميعا الاجتهاد و الكفاح.
Whether it's with this, whether it's with something else,
سواء كان ذلك في هذا الموضوع أو غيره،
we all know what it is to hurt.
كلّنا نعرف ما هو احساس الألم.
We all know what it is to have pain in our heart,
نحن جميعا نعرف ما يكون عليه الألم في قلوبنا،
and we all know how important it is to heal.
وكلنا نعلم كم أنّ الشفاء مهم.
But right now, depression is society's deep cut
ولكن الآن، الاكتئاب هو جرح عميق في المجتمع
that we're content to put a Band-Aid over and pretend it's not there.
نكتفي بتضميده سطحيّا و التظاهر بعدم وجوده.
Well, it is there. It is there, and you know what? It's okay.
لكنه لا يزال هناك. أوتعلمون، لا بأس بذلك.
Depression is okay. If you're going through it, know that you're okay.
لا بأس بالاكتئاب. إن كنت تعاني منه، فاعلم أنّك ستكون على ما يرام.
And know that you're sick, you're not weak,
و اعلم أنّك مريض، و ليس ضعيفا،
and it's an issue, not an identity,
إنّه مشكل و ليس هويّة،
because when you get past the fear and the ridicule
لأنّك عندما تتغلّب عن الخوف و السخرية
and the judgment and the stigma of others,
ومن الحكم ووصمة العار من الآخرين،
you can see depression for what it really is,
يمكنك أن ترى الاكتئاب كما هو عليه فعلا،
and that's just a part of life,
إنّه مجرّد جزء من الحياة،
just a part of life, and as much as I hate,
مجرد جزء من الحياة، وبقدر ما أكره،
as much as I hate some of the places,
بقدر ما أكره بعض الأماكن،
some of the parts of my life depression has dragged me down to,
فإنّ بعض الأجزاء من حياتي قد دفعت بي إلى
in a lot of ways I'm grateful for it.
الكثير من التجارب التي أنا ممتن لها.
Because yeah, it's put me in the valleys,
لأنّها وضعتني في الأسفل،
but only to show me there's peaks,
لكن فقط لتكشف لي أنّ هناك قمما،
and yeah it's dragged me through the dark
و جرّتني إلى الظلام
but only to remind me there is light.
لكن فقط لتذكّرني أنّ هناك ضوءا.
My pain, more than anything in 19 years on this planet,
الألم كان هو طيلة 19 سنة من حياتي أكثر من
has given me perspective, and my hurt,
أعطاني منظورا، و ألمي
my hurt has forced me to have hope,
أجبرني على التّحلي بالأمل
have hope and to have faith, faith in myself,
و الإيمان, الإيمان بنفسي،
faith in others, faith that it can get better,
الثقة في الآخرين، الإيمان أنّ بامكاني التحسّن،
that we can change this, that we can speak up
أنّ بامكاننا تغيير هذا، نستطيع الحديث
and speak out and fight back against ignorance,
عن الأمر و محاربة الجهل،
fight back against intolerance,
محاربة عدم التّقبل،
and more than anything,
وأكثر من أي شيء آخر،
learn to love ourselves,
تعلّم أن نحب أنفسنا،
learn to accept ourselves for who we are,
تعلم أن نتقبّل أنفسنا كما نحن عليه،
the people we are, not the people the world wants us to be.
على ما نحن عليه، و ليس كما يرغب الآخرون منّا أن نكون.
Because the world I believe in is one
لأنّني أؤمن بعالم حيث تقبّل
where embracing your light doesn't mean ignoring your dark.
نورك لا يعني تجاهل جانبك المظلم.
The world I believe in is one where we're measured
أنا أؤمن بعالم حيث يحكم علينا من خلال
by our ability to overcome adversities, not avoid them.
قدرتنا على التغلب على الشدائد، لا تجنبها.
The world I believe in is one where I can look someone in the eye
أنا أؤمن بعالم حيث أستطيع النّظر إلى شخص مباشرة في عينينه
and say, "I'm going through hell,"
و أقول:" أنا أمرّ بجحيم."
and they can look back at me and go, "Me too," and that's okay,
و يتمكّن من إجابتي:"أنا أيضا." و لا بأس بهذا الأمر،
and it's okay because depression is okay. We're people.
لا بأس بالاحساس بالاكتئاب، فنحن بشر.
We're people, and we struggle and we suffer
نحن بشر، فنحن نكافح و نقاسي
and we bleed and we cry, and if you think that true strength
و ننزف و نبكي، و إن كنت تظنّ أنّ القوة الحقيقية
means never showing any weakness, then I'm here
تكمن في عدم إظهار أيّ ضعف، إذا فأنا
to tell you you're wrong.
أقول لك أنّك مخطئ.
You're wrong, because it's the opposite.
أنت مخطئ، فالعكس هو الصحيح.
We're people, and we have problems.
نحن بشر و نواجه مشاكلا.
We're not perfect, and that's okay.
نحن لسنا مثاليّين و لا بأس بذلك.
So we need to stop the ignorance,
إذا فنحن نحتاج أن نضع حدّا للجهل،
stop the intolerance, stop the stigma,
عدم التّقبل، إلى الشعور بالعار،
and stop the silence, and we need to take away the taboos,
و وقف الصمت، ونحن بحاجة إلى التّخلص من التّابوهات،
take a look at the truth, and start talking,
إلقاء نظرة على الحقيقة، وبدء الحديث،
because the only way we're going to beat a problem
لأنّ الطريقة الوحيدة للتغلب على مشكلة ما
that people are battling alone
يواجهها النّاس بصفة فرديّة،
is by standing strong together,
هي في الوقوف معا جنبا إلى جنب،
by standing strong together.
الوقوف معا جنبا إلى جنب.
And I believe that we can.
أعتقد أنّ الأمر ممكن.
I believe that we can. Thank you guys so much.
أؤمن أنّ الأمر ممكن. شكرا جزيلا لكم.
This is a dream come true. Thank you. (Applause)
إنّه حلم يتحقّق. شكرا لكم. (تصفيق)
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)